this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size we're
moving infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
one hundred dollar infrastructure credit
at doco / SC radio for software
engineering radio this is Robert bloomin
today I have with me Ben Siegelman Ben
is the co-founder and CEO of light step
or he is building reliability management
software Ben holds a bachelor's in
mathematics and computer science from
Brown University he is a co-author of
the open tracing standard previously he
built dapper Google's production systems
tracing infrastructure and monarch
Google's fleet-wide time series
collection and analytics system Ben
welcome to software engineering radio
it's a pleasure to be here thanks a lot
for having me Ben today we're going to
be talking about distributed tracing
prior to talking about distributed
tracing I'd like to talk about tracing
in a monolithic or single instance
system and then we'll move on to look at
what are the complexities that are added
by a distributed system let's start with
what is tracing it's a great question
I'm glad you started there because I
think I often forget to do that myself
and then people who have an idea of what
that means can get themselves tied up in
knots the industry has used the word
Tracy
to refer to a bunch of different things
that all have some commonality but
really are quite different so you have
things like stack traces which have that
word trace in them and then you have
things like kernel tracers like D trace
and and it skin and then you have
distributed tracing systems like diapers
again or Jaeger and so on so forth which
you know are really a separate animal in
terms of the common thread I think
really if you talk about all of
monitoring and observability there are
fundamentally two types of data
there's event data and there is
statistical data and that's kind of it
of course those are really broad
categories tracing the tracing data
itself is definitely event data so
that's something that we have in common
across all these domains typically if
you're talking about kernel tracing
you're looking at things that take a
couple of nanoseconds and they happen
very frequently and then you do some
kind of you know indi trace for example
you'd write a script that looks a lot
like an ox script and it will take this
very high frequency stream of events and
then generate a bunch of useful
statistics which you can interpret in
the case of stack traces and that sort
of tracing your you're tracing up the
stack of course everyone is a developer
is seeing a stack trace there's nothing
mysterious about that but it's a totally
different thing than kernel tracing or
distributed tracing and then distributed
tracing I mean you know obviously that
we're distributed is in there what
you're really doing there is you're
looking at a single logical transaction
in assistant so tracing me clarify
statistical data could be things like
not a memory used CPU load or as event
data as here's a lot of particulars
about what happened in this case would
that be accurate differentiation yeah I
think event data has a timestamp that
something happened an event occurred
whereas something like a CPU level is
essentially an aggregate you're saying
over some period of time this is a
summary of what happened a statistical
summary that 75% of the time your CPU is
in a runnable state so that's an apt
description other common statistics
would be things like event rates or
latency percentiles things like that we
had another episode software engineering
radio dealing with logging this sounds
like it might be similar but different
what is the distinction yeah absolutely
logging is very much on the side of
event monitoring that word is also
really problematic in that it means
different things to different people but
but I think logging has come to mean
event monitoring where the cost is
reasonable for centralization you assume
that you can pay to centralize your logs
and then search over them generally
speaking so I think it's really the
events that you can afford to centralize
that that's what the way I think of it
it would be great if you could get you
know every single kernel like every
system call would be great to get all
those into your single Cabana instance
but you can't because it's too expensive
so you don't consider that part of your
logging strategy I'm not sure I at this
point have a great idea of what tracing
is understand it's event data about what
happened in your system could you drill
down into more detail about the thing we
call tracing what differentiates that
from other types of events yeah sure
tracing I think typically in a in a
conventional you know if we go back 15
20 years that kind of thing tracing
usually involves automatic
instrumentation of oftentimes things
that happen at the kernel boundaries so
every system call would be traced or
something like that or you trace every
function call whereas logging usually
implies again these are all
generalizations it usually implies that
a programmer added a logging statement
explicitly to their code so I think
there's a distinction there of course
there's there exceptions to these rules
I got then logging would be
instrumentation that programmers add to
the program to collect data or as
tracing is something that at some level
this is similar to a concept in aspect
oriented programming called a
cross-cutting concern where you can
intercept the normal operation of your
system and collect event data from that
yes and this gets very blurry when you
start talking about more modern
architectures but if we're talking about
the historical context I think that's
totally accurate
okay so in a modern system what are some
of the primary use cases for tracing
well now I think if we're talking about
we need to find modern what that means
to me it means that you're building a
complex piece of software that probably
involves many teams who are working in
concert developing services that work in
concert so you can call that server list
or micro services or what have you but
if you're doing that kind of distributed
development and distributed architecture
that to me is what modern means so in
that kind of modern system I think that
the tracing that we're doing is actually
moving up the stack considerably because
the pain point people are having is
moving up the stack considerably if
you're dealing with a distributed
architecture the kinds of questions
you're trying to answer are actually
very primitive if you're trying to say
things like this transaction was slow or
this transaction had an error I'd
literally have no idea what happened I
have no idea what service is it touched
I have no idea what happened in those
services I have no idea you'd be
thankful if you were at the point where
you're trying to understand what
happened at the system call level you're
actually just trying to figure out which
services were involved and that's a very
different question so distributed
tracing the granularity is actually much
coarser than kernel tracing but it has
this one huge advantage which is that it
can see across system boundaries so if
service a calls because he calls D and D
is having a bad day and it affects
service a you can actually figure that
out very easily and that that's the
profound thing if you didn't have it
before but it's a really different
problem than kernel tracing it sounds
like if you're either trying to figure
out what happened in this case or why's
something taking as long as it did that
tracing it's primarily a troubleshooting
or debugging tool is that accurate this
is a great question I think that's the
answer to that is changing that
certainly I hope it's changing
historically in terms of distributed
tracing it's been used for performance
analysis and for root cause analysis the
performance analysis is often something
where you have a couple of months or a
quarters even to make a performance
improvement and you want to make sure
you focus your energies where it's
actually going to have an effect on the
business so you know anecdotally when I
was at Google before we just you know
before we deployed something like that
we had people spending six months on 20%
performance improvements that were off
the critical path for the end-user so it
literally made no difference and user
latency was not affected by these
performance improvements because they
were in the wrong place
just stupid a trace it can help you
avoid that failure mode the other use
case is that you know you're woken up at
3:00 in the morning you know that
something bad is happening I need you
you need to figure out where as quickly
as possible and if you're working in a
distributed environment a tracing system
can be really helpful with that in both
cases you're actually looking at
individual traces to make these
assessments I think that where I see the
industry heading is to see this
underlying data the distributed tracing
data as a fount of knowledge about how
these distributed systems interact and
to observe higher-level insights and
surface higher-level insights to
developers operators and even management
to better understand these systems and I
can of course expand on that but I think
we're really in early days and it's
going to be a lot more powerful than
looking at individual traces in a UI I
do want to come back to that higher
level insights but let's stay on the
troubleshooting and low level stuff for
a bit the idea of critical path analysis
explain what that is yeah thanks for
asking so the idea is that if you're
operating in a modern environment
there's a lot of concurrency in the
system that you're that you're
developing so if you call everything in
serial it would take you know days to
get back to users if you're operating
with hundreds of services so you do
things in parallel now if you were to
call out to five services in parallel
and you have to wait for all of them to
return the one that comes back lasts
delays the end user it's it's obvious
the one that comes back last is on the
critical path that's really the idea
it's that you need to look whenever this
concurrency or parallelize parallelism
you need to go back understand what the
laggard was and focus your analysis
there it's an easy thing to do
automatically and programmatically if
you have the structural information
which distributed traces do to help with
that analysis so a good tracing system
should help you surface the critical
path automatically so you don't waste
time analyzing things that aren't
actually holding up the end user or the
transaction at the
the stuff we did another show about
latency and latency outliers on that
show we covered the idea that latency
outliers are far more important to the
human perception of the responsiveness
of a system but these are things that
don't occur by definition very often is
tracing something that would help you
identify what are the one tenth of a
percentile of the worst performing
requests that you served absolutely
especially if the tracing system is
designed in a way that allows it to
focus as energies in those areas and I
think that again is something that I
think about all the time is absolutely a
useful technology for that now you said
one of the use cases is figure out what
happened I might say well we built the
system we should know what it does but I
understand the person who's on call when
the alert goes off may not know that
system a calls five other systems today
that it didn't call yesterday because no
one no one told him is tracing a good
reverse engineering tool for operations
I would argue it's the best reverse
engineering tool that's why people get
excited about it
there are a lot of difficulties with
tracing and practice but that's the
value prop is that in that situation
where you need the information it's just
right there in front of you that's
almost by definition of what it's doing
okay now we're gonna drill down into
more detail about what goes on in
tracing and I promise we will get to
distributed tracing but I want to go
through some fundamental concepts that
will enable us to have this language to
have this discussion there are concepts
that are in the literature I was reading
to prepare for this show and I want you
to explain what these are the first one
being a transaction that's an
interesting one I have a definition of
it that I feel very confident about but
I've seen other people use other
definitions of it that are in conflict
with my own but I think a transaction
ought to be considered as
a single logical unit of work in its
entirety so I say I say in its entirety
to emphasize the fact that the
transaction may move from process to
process or for a machine to machine or
thread to thread and it's still the same
transaction there are other people that
define a transaction to be scoped to a
single VM and then when it moves to
another VM even if it's part of the same
unit of work that's considered its own
transaction I think that is limited and
limiting as a definition so it's not the
one I subscribe to
but that's hopefully that answers your
question at least from my perspective
could you give an example of a
transaction either something you worked
on at Google or at another project sure
I mean a web search is a perfectly fine
example that we can all relate to so you
type your query the transaction actually
begins in your browser it goes through a
number of front-end layers it ends up in
a in you know it's no secret that Google
runs something called quiz GWS which is
the Google web server which is where the
logic starts happening it farms it out
to you know dozens and dozens of
different services that all take a crack
at your query Google takes the results
from all those things and combines them
into a result set and then presents it
to you now if you abyss caches along the
way that transaction will involve
literally you know thousands to tens of
thousands of different VMs before it
comes back to you in a quarter of a
second and that's what a cache miss
looks like for Google cache hit of
course can be much cheaper but these
transactions are very very elaborate
sure does the transaction include if
your request places some work on a queue
to be done later and then that work gets
done later is that part of the
transaction oh you're asking all the
hard questions so that's an area of
debate I I think if the queue is simply
a go it's it's just a FIFO queue one in
one out kind of thing yeah totally if
your queue is doing batching so an
example I would give is a lot of
high-throughput storage systems like
Cassandra HBase or a big table at Google
things like that they'll do some kind of
log structured right where you'll do the
right it'll transact it'll return to the
user and you continue doing your thing
and then later it'll take a sequence of
Rights and consolidate them into one
read optimize block and that ends up
being very expensive so if you're trying
to profile these things you need to
understand where all that expenses
coming from and unfortunately it comes
from many transactions because there's
batching so whenever there's batching
the notion of what a transaction
actually is gets to be kind of difficult
at the end of the dabber paper that I
helped to write we talked about this as
being a pernicious issue for us from an
analytical standpoint and I don't think
that there's a very clear way of saying
one way or the other if that's one
transaction or many transactions it is
true that if you consider to be one
transaction your transactions get to be
very large because you have this it's no
longer a tree it's a graph and the full
graph can it can suck up your entire
system I'm thinking if I care about
latency and that's the use case then
work that's going to be done later is
not going to count toward latency but if
I was more interested in what are all
the steps in serving this request I
would potentially care about work that's
going to be done later is that correct I
wish it was I really wish it was it's
almost correct that it's certainly
correct in our mental model let me go
back to the example I was giving so in
my experience if you have a system where
latency degrades without a software
release it's I'm not gonna put a number
on it but let's let's say almost all the
time it's because something is
overloaded so most most sudden
production latency regressions are due
to throughput so you have some kind of
overwhelming throughput in a system and
that creates a bottleneck and in
queueing Theory if there's a bottleneck
and you start falling behind things go
haywire and the haywire is reflected in
very high latency so the problem there
is now you need to understand where that
load came from and going back to the
example you're just speaking about since
you know we already went through it if
you have some kind of storage system and
the CPU is getting really hot it's
probably because of this kind of
consolidation and batching and that's a
matter of looking at all these other
requests so unfortunately these requests
are you're right in the sense that that
the requests can be thought of in
isolation but the requests from a couple
of minutes ago that are getting
batched and are causing you to saturate
CP you are actually affecting latency
for requests that are happening minutes
later and understanding that kind of
root cause analysis is very very
challenging because the amount of data
is so overwhelming that if you
centralize all of it you're you're not
going to be able to afford your
observability system and if you don't
you literally lack the information to to
run that analysis and that's that's the
problem you just now mention the data
that is collected I'm gonna come back to
that also I want to move on at this
moment to another important concept in
tracing which is the idea of context and
propagation could you address that yeah
totally so in a in a tracing system you
know primarily a distributed tracing
system but not necessarily this can
happen in a single host system as well
it's important to understand the threat
of execution
I probably shouldn't use the word threat
it doesn't necessarily have to be a
single threat like in a JavaScript
environment and node the continuation
local storage is often where you put
this context and that will actually move
from logical thread to logical thread
but the idea that I'm trying to get at
here is that you need to understand the
sequence of events that affect a single
transaction and the context object is
usually the thing where you store some
kind of central identifier or other
state that you can use to tie those that
sequence of events together it gets
tricky because the context will four can
join as we were saying earlier to make
things faster we do things concurrently
so the context literally splits in half
and then rejoins later and there's a lot
of theory around that but the idea of
context is incredibly important to
understanding transaction traces let's
go back to this Google search example
what are some interesting fields or data
that would be in the context so the
approach that we took with dapper was
honestly pretty simplistic but it was
effective which was to have two unique
IDs one was called the trace ID which
lived for the entirety of this one
transaction and the other was called a
span ID and a span is one logical
segment of that trace that doesn't have
any internal forking and joining of its
own
and is quote-unquote the right size to
measure in a system like this that
basically means that you're not going to
have a span for every system call but
you probably will have a span for every
remote procedure call or HTTP call or
something like that so the trace ID is
consistent for the entire trace the span
IDs are unique within that trace and
then you form a grat well in diapers
case a tree more formally theoretically
a graph of spans pointing to their
parents and that allows you to infer the
structure of the transaction and get
things like the critical path out so the
context will contain a trace and span ID
we went further eventually the census
project at Google not to be confused
with the open census project which
derives from it the census project added
the originating service so if the
request initially came from a user in
Google web search or a gmail user or a
calendar easer etc etc that product ID
was essentially encoded and used for
resource accounting which is actually a
really profound application of this
underlying tracing that has nothing to
do with latency analysis and I think
it's important for people to understand
the applications of this technology are
much broader than observability and it
really comes back to the context rather
than the latency measurements in that
case I'm hoping to get something more
concrete like the name of each service
visits the IP address maybe the stack
trace or call stack on that process what
kind of things that's not in the context
so let me try again I'll be less verbose
the context
there's really two types of data that
you want to record one is the data that
you record in band which is to say if if
you're sending a request from service a
to service B you have to pass some
contexts along in band along with
application data and then the other data
is out-of-band the in band data is very
small all you want to do is record
unique IDs so in dapper we recorded a
trace ID that was consistent for the
entire transaction and what we call the
span ID which represents that one
service call in the out-of-band channel
you record much more detailed
information so all the timing
information all of the
tags the names of things the names the
services names of end points even like a
micro log of events that took place for
each span that's all sent out of band
and buffered and that does not need to
happen in real time you just get it out
of the process as efficiently as you can
but there's this very thick buffered out
of band channel in this very thin spell
in band context which just records
unique IDs this sounds something like
how log aggregation to a log message to
the log aggregator in band during the
work the program is doing as long as it
gets queued up and later gets collected
exactly the same and you may have said
this or maybe I'm inferring this this
idea is it going to enable you to
correlate all the different collections
that occurred across many different
servers and then you're gonna have this
more detailed data that will get stored
with that key so that you're able to
match up all these different pieces of
context exactly okay do we Trace
exceptional conditions or errors as well
as the thing that it was supposed to do
or that we wanted it to do
we should and we should yeah I think
generally speaking it's a goal for
systems like this to have extra detail
what things aren't going well and an
error would be an example of that both
soft errors and hard errors and some
tracing systems are better at dealing
with that situation than others and that
gets into sampling which we haven't
discussed yet how big in a case like the
Google search example where you're
hitting a bunch of different servers it
might be add spellcheck search indexes
how big is the data is collected for a
single search good question it does vary
but the rule of thumb is that an
individual span which is a single
segment of the trace is usually between
100 and 1000 bytes so you can kind of do
the math if you have a couple thousand
spans you know you're talking about
something in the order of single-digit
megabytes of data for
these traces we've been talking now
about the concepts involved in tracing
and some of the plumbing of how it works
you have mentioned the distributed
systems case where you're propagating
this idea across processes I do want to
dive into distributed tracing now what
makes that harder than tracing in a
single process well earlier I was saying
that in conventional single system
tracing it's usually done via some kind
of automatic instrumentation of function
calls or system calls or something like
that in the case of distributed tracing
we wish very much that we had something
like that to lean on and that's actually
what the open tracing project is
attempting to accomplish for everyone's
benefit but we don't so you end up
either having to build some kind of
software agent that attempts to do this
through brute force and monkey patching
and introspection which i think is
honestly just impossible to do without
overhead or you have to write a bunch of
instrumentation so the number one
problem with distributed tracing
historically has been that
instrumentation is hard at Google we
could cheat because things were so well
factored that you could make
instrumentation you could add
instrumentation to a very small subset
of the code base and get huge coverage
there are only a few companies in the
world that operate at scale and have
that property so instrumentation is is
quite difficult for distributed tracing
a typical distributed system these days
you're crossing over a lot of stuff you
don't own like nginx
an H a proxy things written in different
languages which could be go Python Java
Ruby and then when you get into code
that you own it's going through layers
and layers of framework functions before
it calls into your code all of these
things could be somehow relevant not
just the code that you wrote how do you
get instrumentation in all these layers
that you didn't build this is
absolutely the right question to ask the
purpose of projects like open tracing is
to address that problem so open tracing
actually does have an implementation
that allows for introspection into
engine X and H a proxy you know and many
of the other technologies you mentioned
and has supported and ten languages now
and also supported by many of the I said
earlier that things are getting blurrier
in the modern world what I meant by that
is the separation between what I would
consider to be business logic or
application code and the libraries that
serves the purpose of of a kernel
boundary but are not by any means the
kernel is getting quite blurry there are
a lot of things that we depend on things
like RPC libraries like G RPC or sidecar
systems like envoy and Sto things like
this feel to me at an emotional level
like the kernel used to feel and yet
they're absolutely not the kernel and
those things need to be instrumented
out-of-the-box or you're going to drive
yourself crazy and so we need to have a
standard way of describing transactions
that is literally the purpose of open
tracing that is why we did it so that
you don't need to have every developer
hand instrument all this stuff much of
which is incredibly unfriendly to
instrumentation to begin with and so we
try to solve that problem once in a way
that's vendor neutral and implementation
neutral and that's the purpose of that
project is to address that and I think
it's been pretty successful with that
okay I want to talk about open tracing
but I've one more question that's in
this propagation area very common now
applications interface with an API to
something else let's say for example I
work on our product that integrates with
Facebook it's calling Facebook api's
waiting gets a response back do you want
to would you ideally like to propagate
your context all the way to Facebook and
back or is that a black box that becomes
one thing just one thing in the final
result well there's what you'd like and
what's realistic I think would be
wonderful to propagate that context to
Facebook and back and have insight into
their system
so that would mean that there's a
technical problem that we have to solve
and also that Facebook is willing to
share that information with outside
world which they're definitely not so I
think that there's almost a business
concern that's going to prevent that
kind of reality from from taking hold
there is a nice standards effort that's
led by a number of different vendors
that's presently at w3c project to
standardize on the propagation formats
and all of their excruciating detail and
one of the end goals for that is to
develop ways for vendors like Facebook
in this case to return helpful
information beyond how long this thing
took to help you understand how you
could make it faster or if you're doing
something wrong so something like an
explained query and sequel that is just
always on for any sass that you depend
on I think would be a really useful
thing for Facebook and for its its
developer users and I would love to see
that take place and seem as realistic
it's it's something that we think about
at live stuff in that we have many of
our customers or actually customers of
each other and since we're collecting
all the tracing information about both
we actually have the data we have
customer a is calling customer B's
Giants ass and we have both sides of the
transaction of course it you know we
have contracts that forbid us from
connecting the dots for them but it's
ironic and that we actually have the
whole thing and I'm sure it'd be
valuable to the caller to see that
information
you mentioned open tracing a number of
times as solving some of these issues
that are otherwise hard to solve what is
open tracing and how does it solve the
problems of implementing tracing yeah
open tracing is an intentionally narrow
project I think that for people who
haven't had much exposure to distributed
tracing there's a tendency to focus on
the UI aspects of it but when you get
into the implementation especially the
instrumentation side of it the diversity
of systems you need to integrate with to
come up with a coherent truly global
trace is just overwhelming and open
tracing is specifically focused on that
one aspect of the problem there are
three problems in tracing one is
gathering data one is centralized in
that data which probably involves a lot
of trickery like sampling and things
like that and then one is actually
analyzing that data and presenting it to
human beings so you know if you ask
people to draw a picture of a computer
they draw a monitor right it's the same
thing we tend to think of the UI or the
analytical features as tracing but the
first third of that problem the
instrumentation a data gathering piece
is just enormous ly complicated in
practice and open tracing really only
concerns itself with that so it takes
the form of a series of api's that are
standard across languages and our our
coherent and consistent across languages
both with each other and with the
languages themselves idiomatically and
then it also takes the form of diaspora
of instrumentation at this point
covering many hundreds of projects that
are supporting open tracing at this
point and the idea is that if you depend
on one of those projects you don't need
to instrument that thing it's already
done so again you mentioned things like
nginx and H a proxy earlier those are
examples of things that can support up
and tracing but also software layers you
know anything and the job at Yukos it's
like JD PC or drop Wizard or or rx Java
it really the list goes on on to Python
and Django and flask and node has
expressed support and so on and so forth
all these major frameworks that people
depend on have open tracing support
either natively or via plugins and that
means if you depend on those you don't
need to instrument them yourself so as
an application developer it takes away
this massive front-loaded pain point of
instrumentation and that's the value
prop and tracing I want to go more into
the collection I'll take Java as an
example cuz I'm familiar with it there's
ability to attach something called an
agent to the JVM which can hook itself
into what the JVM is doing and it could
collect information like this I
understand other languages have
something similar to that is that how
you would implement the tracing
collection by packing into the language
runtime so conventional APM vendors
AppDynamics and New Relic are great
examples of this as a static trace use
things like Java agents almost to the
exclusion of other techniques to gather
this information and there are a lot of
advantages to that the most obvious one
is that as a user of these systems
you don't need to make any code
modifications to take advantage of these
agents and that's actually really
wonderful the troubles are overhead
which can become an issue high
throughput and I think is unacceptable
for production applications and the
correctness and robustness and
durability of the instrumentation itself
so if you're trying to instrument
something trivial that probably works
but if you're trying to instrument
something where there's a lot of
internal concurrency and so on and so
forth the the agent instrumentation that
you're writing has to actually match the
particular minor version of the thing
that you're you're depending on and
that's fragile
it's just fragile there's nothing more
to it it's something that's why there
aren't open source implementations and
things like this that are very reliable
because it requires a huge staff of
people to maintain those
instrumentations and I think that that's
unsustainable it's also quite wasteful
from just an industrial standpoint
they're spending most of their
engineering effort maintaining these
couplings between specific versions of
libraries and their particular data
formats and a model like open tracing
allows for cleaner white box
instrumentation of those systems it does
not preclude the idea that you could
also have an agent I think data dog has
an APM that uses open tracing support
and wraps it with a Java agent to
prevent you from having to do any as a
gluing of white box instrumentation to
your applications main line so these are
not mutually exclusive techniques but I
think that the hand instrumentation of
every library Under the Sun is really
unsustainable and that's that's the part
that I would argue against how does open
tracing do it then without these agents
it does it through it's just literally
code it's the same thing that you see
with metrics if you look into software
systems that are designed for just you
know distribution to a micro services
environment metrics are now part of the
code base and I think instrumentation
like this should also be part of the
code base just like unit tests or
something like that I think it's as
important if not more important than a
lot of those other things that we've
come to accept will be part of the
maintained code base that mean then if
the nginx maintainer zhh want their
product to be traceable they would add
some trace statements to nginx and I
might run a slightly different version
of it or set some flags in my conf that
tell it to enable open trace
yeah I think that there's a couple of
different approaches that people have
taken one is design to design a general
purpose usually callback driven way to
observe a system like nginx and the
other is to bake some kind of
instrumentation open tracing or
otherwise directly into the codebase and
and then for a configuration of getting
getting the data out I believe that in
nginx this case that could be done via
environment variables or via
configuration statements where you
couple the instrumentation to some kind
of downstream sync that you want to send
it to which is usually I'd open trace an
open trace and compliant tracing system
or some kind of commercial of APM vendor
I've got a move on now and talk about
the data and then we'll talk about the
backend and getting data out of it the
data that is collected we we had some
discussion of there's the larger
out-of-band data set that can get queued
up and sent to the backend how does the
data get from the collection point to
the backend is there some kind of
sidecar type process that runs on the
instance and handles that communication
that varies because quite widely
actually there are different ways to do
it one of my personal axes to grind is
that there are people trying to say
there's a right way of doing that I
think it entirely depends on what you're
trying to accomplish there are people
that it's important that for instance
they want to make sure that if the
process seg faults or something like
that or has some kind of fatal exception
that you don't miss that transaction
that had the fatal exception so
naturally in that case you can't delay
sending data out you need to do it
synchronously which naturally has a lot
of overhead that's not wrong it's just
it's a requirement that you have whereas
there are other situations where you
don't care about that at all and you're
just concerned with making sure that you
have the lowest overhead possible and
that you're always on production that
demands a different type of application
of data collection so I think there are
many different ways to do it if um
architecture that's probably someone
who's who's doing that right now and I
strongly urged the industry not to try
and pick a single thing I think it
depends on the requirements but it
varies from synchronous offloading to on
dispatching - you know sidecar processes
to remote collection it's it's all over
the map I could if I had a
multi-threaded language have a thread
that was the tracing collector thread
that was doing this or I could dump it
out to a log file have something like
log aggregator that was tailing that and
picking it up and sending it somewhere
those are all options mm-hmm yeah and
there there are also systems like a
source graph open sourced tracing system
that called app - that actually builds
the entire tracing system into the
process it's a it's a golang based
system and you can actually go to a port
and use a fully fledged tracing system
that's linked into the process itself
and it does everything as you know part
of the process which of course has its
disadvantages but it's also really easy
to deploy so again it really the the
variation is pretty extreme there's a
lot of heterogeneity you're talking
about how you might do this at each step
is open tracing that's an aimed at
creating interoperability of what part
of the whole tracing infrastructure open
tracing that the goal there is to be
intentionally narrow and to describe the
transaction and specify almost nothing
about how that description is used it's
possible to use that description to run
you know a dapper style tracing system
like zip beginner Jaeger it's also
possible to build completely different
applications on top of that solo IO
which is a startup that has done some
really great open-source work recently
announced distributed debugger that uses
open tracing as the underlying firmament
so you can create breakpoints and print
statements in a distributed application
and debug it and production using open
tracing instrumentation as the as the
lingua franca for describing stop points
and things like that
there's another startup I'm aware of
that's going to be doing building a
technology that allows you to write
integration tests against a distributed
system using open tracing
instrumentation again as the lingua
franca so you can say something like you
know using my example from earlier
service a calls be called C cos T you
can write a test for service a that says
if I call service D I want to assert
this invariant that gets passed through
the context mechanism and open tracing
and the assertion is validated and
service D and it will you know your test
will fail if it's not valid that's a
really powerful thing to be able to do
that and at the moment most people write
integration tests that do some horrible
hack to get the data out of the process
somehow centralize it and then do string
comparison it's very difficult to scale
that type of operational thing so a lot
of people just don't write their
integration tests anymore and and things
like open tracing can help you write
that sort of application and again I'm
trying to emphasize that these have
nothing to do with latency analysis the
common thread is that you need to
understand how the transaction
propagates that is the only thing that
open tracing does is a huge problem it's
more than enough for one project and I
think it's really important that the
scope is super super narrow for that
reason
continuing more into the back end the
data we've been talking about gets
collected at each node and gets
forwarded to some kind of back-end what
is that back-end look like it you know
generally it varies if you're talking
about someone who's running a
quote-unquote conventional distributed
tracing system I think that the back end
usually has a couple of pieces there's a
piece that's trying to absorb the the
segments of these traces and assemble
them into their actual distributed
transactions and then you store that
somewhere it's typically in some kind of
key value store it doesn't make a whole
lot of difference and then there's some
other piece of it that at a high levels
indexing those and that can mean a lot
of different things I think in the case
of sibian it's literally a parametric
search where you say I want this service
between these times and above this
latency and then you hit search and it
comes back with a list in other cases of
something a lot more elaborate and you
try to derive times threes data or
histograms from this stuff it really
varies quite quite widely but the sky's
the limit analytic
I think look back in then to restate
it's some kind of database it's
capturing the data and indexing it to
support queries that implement the
different use cases that we've been
discussing yes and and one I would
caution the world at talking about
tracing as a product tracing as a
technology if it's not properly
integrated with other technologies you
will not have the use cases you need so
I think there's a mistake right now
where I think we're often talking about
tracing as if it's a product it's a
technology period and if it's not
properly integrated with metrics and
other things like that
you will be unsatisfied from a workflow
standpoint and I honestly think many
people are unsatisfied with tracing
because they deploy something that's
only capable of showing a trace and
that's not a workflow so it's important
that we as end as consumers of this
technology that we're thinking about the
workflow were trying to satisfy and
choosing our tools and technologies
appropriately to satisfy those workflows
and not to assume well if I deploy
tracing then I'll be able to do root
cause analysis it doesn't work like that
in cases you've seen what are some of
the more popular databases that people
are using in the back end this be
elastic search or Cassandra or what are
some examples I think for open source
tracing systems typically that's exactly
right I think by default Zipkin and the
agri both stored the trace data in
Cassandra and I think I could be wrong
but I think both support elastic search
as you know as an indexing system to
surface individual traces upon making
some kind of parametric query that is in
my mind an implementation detail of
those products if we want to use that
terminology and I don't think it should
be something that people are necessarily
particularly concerned with as and as
consumers of that except obviously if
you want to save some operational effort
and you know not spin up an additional
sub service
based on our discussions so far I'm
trying to think of what are some queries
I might like to run against the back end
I could imagine if I have a given
request I could say Givens request ID
let me see all the services that it
touched or let me see all the requests
in this period of time when the system
was badly behaving that hit a particular
service let me see the worst latency
performing requests and where did they
spend most of their time am I going in
the right direction with these ideas I
think you are although I don't mean this
to sound like a product pitch for light
step but there are a lot of things that
you can do with light step that you
can't do with conventional tracing
system and they're designed to answer
questions that I think are of higher
level interest so an example might be
something like this like I have my my
company has a million accounts a hundred
of them generate 75% of my revenue I
want to know within seconds of the
single one of those 100 accounts moving
outside of SOA and I want to see the
history of performance for that account
for the operations they care the most
about and I want to see examples of
transactions that violate the SLA from
the last ten seconds and I want you to
do that all the time and then you tell
me when I'm violating my SLA and a
tracing system can do that too and I
think that's a much higher level
business need and I think is a better
application of that technology then
forcing the developer to cough up a
request ID or something like that I mean
they may have it in which case that's
great but it's um it's probably not
something to be counted on you haven't
asked me about sampling but sampling is
also really important most tracing
systems have to do some kind of sampling
the amount of data you start with is so
vast that you can't store it centralize
all of it and I don't think there's an
exception to that rule the way that
sampling is performed is incredibly
important here if you have a specific
request to do that you're interested in
in dapper we sampled one out of 10,000
requests and was done randomly so almost
for sure that one requests ID is nowhere
to be found
so if sampling isn't done with some kind
of intelligence and with some with the
benefit of retroactive analysis it's
unlikely that you're going to have the
specific transactions you're looking for
so sampling also comes into play here in
a major way
yeah I could see that would be a way to
control the vast amount of data you
would have to collect if you try to
collect everything going back now to
these use cases the ones I came up with
we're all an individual user I have a
problem I'm trying to get information
about it I think what you're talking
about is you can have machine being the
user of this data it can be extracting
metrics and those could feed into
monitoring and alerting system where you
you wouldn't be able to get this
information out of conventional
monitoring which generally deals with a
single instance or single request so
it's a way of getting more useful or
actionable data out of your system by
processing it through tracing so the
examples that I thought of were
individual user I have a problem I'm
trying to get some information out of it
it sounds like where you're seeing some
great use cases is that you have machine
users other systems which pull
information out of tracing that then
goes into monitoring or alerting am I
going in the right direction with that
absolutely and I again that that's
exactly what I'm saying about workflows
I think the workflows are that you want
to know early about leading indicators
of unhealthy behavior in your system and
that's typically the domain of
monitoring there's literally no reason
that we shouldn't be building monitoring
signals off of this raw data from
tracing systems that is absolutely the
right way to do it and this is what I'm
getting a bit this is what I'm getting
at with tracing as the technology it's
not a product the tracing technology
must be integrated into those workflows
so if you get woken up at 3:00 in the
morning imagine the difference between a
page that this says latency is high good
luck open your laptop and a page that
says latency is high here are five or 15
or 50 examples of transactions from the
last minute that exemplify this
violation for SLA and that will show you
how you bottomed out on a specific
system is overloaded it's this night and
day absolutely
I mean from a customer standpoint I know
for sure that this improves root cause
analysis times by 90 something percent
it's a significant change in behavior
you mentioned earlier one of the
potential families of use cases is
higher level insights and analytics
describe how you could give an example
of how you could derive some useful
insights from analytics based on this
data that you've collected
you mentioned sampling a few times I
feel like I should ask you to give a
overview of the relationship of sampling
to tracing yeah so the trouble is
tracing is that the amount of data we're
collecting is absolutely overwhelming at
a theoretical level so somewhere there
needs to be some sampling before you get
to centralized repository that's indexed
and analyzed and kept forever
the traditional approach was to just do
random sampling
so at dapper we've sampled one out of
10,000 requests some APM vendors have
done sampling where they'll wait for a
bad request and then sample the next one
in hopes that it has the same issue in
light step we've decided to collect all
the data for some period of time and
then do retroactive sampling based on
features that we discover there are
different approaches but sampling ends
up allowing or disallowing you to do
different analytical things down the
line and is one of the most important
design decisions in a tracing system I
want to come back to earlier you said
one of the use cases is gaining
higher-level insights from analytics can
you give some examples of that yeah so
teeing off of the sampling discussion I
think a lot of it depends on what sort
of sampling strategy you took if you
went to some kind of random or
pseudo-random sampling it's often
difficult to do much more than look at
individual transactions so hopefully
what you can do is find ones that are
interesting and bubble up things like
critical path analysis which we referred
to earlier and things like that you can
also infer a system diagram pretty
easily from tracing data in the
aggregate it may be missing a
transaction here there but you'll get
the general picture will be accurate
the thing that's interesting if you have
an approach that allows you to see all
the transactions you can going back to
this I think very common case of having
a high latency event really boiling down
to an overloaded system tracing can do
some really profound things in that case
so let's imagine that you depend on a
sequel database and that the sequel
database is getting slow it's almost
certainly because something is hammering
the sequel database that's if something
suddenly changes in sequel is almost
always because something's hammering
sequel so imagines a system that can
automatically detect that the sequel
database is slow which is easy to
observe because everything that depends
on it is now slow as well but it can
also look at changes in the ingress so
you can use the distributed tracing
information to find the pattern and what
changed in the data going into sequel
what changed in the query pattern not
just locally but where did that come
from and you can even pinpoint it to a
specific software release way up the
stack where something you know started a
cascade of events that resulted in
overwhelming you see your sequel
database that can be automated
it truly automated if you have both the
downward and upwards information about
tracing and can be flexible about
sampling to go back and do that analysis
with the benefit of a full fidelity I've
worked on problems like that and one of
the challenges is you have to be looking
at the system when the problem is
happening what I think you're saying is
if you capture this data then you can
work backwards from the problem upstream
to the cause ex-post using the data that
you collected exactly led steps approach
is to keep a circularbuffer that's
usually at least five minutes long it
can be much longer if customers want to
provision for it but you basically have
several minutes to discover that
something bad is happening by you I mean
the system not a human being so the
system will observe that latency is not
healthy and then will say oh this is bad
I'm going to do a very deep analysis to
understand what happened and then just
automatically just collect a battalion
of these traces and do aggregate
analysis on them in reaction to those
events so it's a combination of of the
two fundamental Act
in monitoring one is measuring symptoms
and the other is explaining them if you
can measure symptoms continuously and
automatically detect an anomaly which is
not rocket science from a stat
standpoint then you can tie that with
automatic automatic root cause analysis
and tracing data is kind of a skeleton
key for doing that in a distributed
system I want to move on this will be
our last main topic adoption suppose we
built a system we did not build tracing
in from the ground up and now we want to
adopt it what are the steps in adoption
so in an environment where you have
developers that are actively
contributing to these code bases it's
not a lot of work to add tracing I think
it's important that it's done
intelligently and that it's it's not
done as a company-wide cross-cutting
effort where everyone instruments their
systems in the same day you need to
start at the core of your business where
there's actually a lot of value to be
had from performance information and
again it can be managed and it's not
that bad
in a system where you have a bunch of
legacy code where there's not a
developer staffed to maintain the code
base that gets harder and I think things
like software agents actually have an
important part to play in that story
that's a longer road for sure and then
in systems where it's not just legacy
code it's just literally not yours like
you depend on a vendor or something like
that to provide just a black box that's
the kind of worst case scenario from an
instrumentation standpoint and then we
rely on standards efforts like the ones
we referred to earlier to get those
vendors to provide some level of of
transparency into what's happening
within their particular black box so
it's kind of a spectrum the thing that's
maybe a gray area are open source open
source components that are under active
development but not by you and that's an
area where I think standards projects
like open tracing can have a huge amount
of value in that they can factor that
problem out for everyone's benefit both
the the open source developers the app
developers at some large organization
and then of course vendors and tracing
systems that want to consume that data
all benefit from some kind of standard
at that layer
if we're adopting tracing in an existing
system is it more on the end of the
spectrum where you get proportional
benefit as you roll it out or more like
you don't really get any benefit until
you've really done it nearly everywhere
thankfully it's not the latter but I
think what the anti pattern I've seen is
people naturally are conservative and so
if you want to integrate a new
technology you'll start at the periphery
of your system and that's a bad idea if
you start with something peripheral
nobody cares about what you find so if
you're instrumenting something that's of
no business value even if you discover
something interesting from a latency
standpoint it's not interesting from a
business standpoint so the most
important thing is to ya sure be
conservative about it start small but
start at the core of your system start
somewhere where it really matters when
light step was this getting kicked off
as a company our customers were
naturally skeptical because we had
nothing to lean on except for just our
you know groveling and promises and so
they would they would integrate us into
the periphery of their systems and it
was difficult to deliver value there but
then when they moved us into the core it
was really only 5% of their system or
something like that it wasn't a big
instrumentation effort but it delivered
a huge amount of value that was
differentiated against what they had
previously and so I think most companies
that are adopting tracing whether it's
from a vendor or using Jaeger or
whatever the strategy that works best is
to look to think about it really from a
business standpoint which transactions
are most valuable to my business and
those are the areas that you should
focus on so you should think about how
to answer questions with these traces
that will actually matter to somebody
from a KPI standpoint and then the
effort goes much more smoothly even if
there's a gap in the trace and you have
a you have an area where there's there's
something on a critical path that's
clearly missing information I guarantee
you getting someone to add that data is
gonna be a lot easier if you can say hey
you know this is really important to our
top customers that we understand what
happened within your service and that's
gonna be much more motivating than just
asking nicely without that evidence
within our software development
organization are the advocates of
tracing adoption is that usually
developers DevOps ops
who is really pushing for this
DevOps is one of those words that means
a lot of different things to different
people but if we're talking about people
who both write code and carry pagers for
instance just you know morally speaking
I know that it's probably just their
phone or whatever but that audience
definitely hears about this kind of
stuff if you're getting woken up by a
system and you know how to make changes
to the code base you definitely care
about this kind of thing we also see a
lot of enthusiasm for this type of
technology from engineering management
actually which stands to reason and that
Conway's law dictates that you know your
order charts going to resemble your
system architecture and with
micro-services that's just even more
obvious and it's an important managerial
tool as well because going back to the
service a/b c/d thing if service D is
having a really bad day you don't want
to pin that on service a B and C even
though they're also having a bad day
because they depend on service D so it's
important from a managerial standpoint
to be able to understand within your
organization where the latency problems
are coming from and tracing is actually
a pretty valuable tool for that since
the systems are getting so large that
the developers don't often understand
these dependencies themselves then
moving into the wrap-up here is there
anything else you'd like to say about
this topic that we haven't covered I
think you've actually asked really
excellent questions and I appreciate
especially that you started with the
high level of what is tracing and in
what is the stupid tracing and to
differentiate from it the one thing that
I would maybe want to emphasize and that
I think is not well understood is that
in the movement towards quote unquote
observability which is you know the
modern way of talking about how you make
sense of these systems for creating
there is a lot of talk about logging
metrics and tracing as being the three
pillars and I think that's baloney I
really do I like a lot of people who say
it but I think is total baloney I think
we need to talk about use cases and
workflows that's it there's only two of
them really you measure symptoms and you
explain them but we need to think about
the technologies we use in the frame of
those workflows it's the most important
point if I could make one point it's
that point and that if you deploy
tracing without understanding in detail
how those workflows are going to play
out you'll probably be disappointed and
I think it's the you know it's the
single most important thing to think
about when you're talking about adopting
this type of
nology and then the other thing I would
maybe add as a secondary note is that
instrumentation it seems daunting but
it's not that bad I think if you if you
rely on standards open tracing those
made things a lot better if you rely on
standards and you're focused in the way
you adopt the stuff and don't try to do
a cross-cutting change across your
entire company it's actually quite
doable and delivers a lot of value
really quickly Ben if people would like
to see any content you produce or reach
out to you where is the best place well
you can always reach out to me I like
email from strangers and my email
address can probably be distributed with
the show as far as I'm concerned but
it's BHS at light step calm or BHS at
gmail.com which I got as a favor from a
friend when I was still working at
Google but you're welcome to send me an
email in terms of talks and so on I did
a talk a number of talks at PubCon over
the last couple of years that I think
have covered the high level of tracing
and and have talked about some of the
nuances that we've discussed in the show
but with video and demos and so on so
forth so those are probably things I'd
recommend you mentioned light step your
company and I mentioned open tracing
work and people get more involved with
open tracing open tracing is a really
vibrant open source project that has
contributors both on open tracing core
api's as well as on the vendor and open
source tracing system side as well as in
the Diaspora of software systems that
support tracing and the contributions
are welcome in any part of that they
should go to open tracing IO and just
you know since I'm going to note we use
getter really heavily for a light step
you're welcome to reach out to me if you
want but if you go to our website it's
easy to to experience the product
through that through that channel as
well Ben siegelman thank you very much
for speaking to software engineering
radio thank you so much for having me
this has been Robert bloomin for a
software engineering radio and thank you
for listening
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening